Guide to the Marcel Kurpershoek Papers AD.MC.054
NYU Abu Dhabi, Archives and Special Collections
- Printed material: copied books and texts in Arabic and English
  - Ḥamza, Fuʼād. Qalb Jazīrat al-ʻArab [Heart of the Arabian Peninsula]. ([Makka]: al-Maktaba al-Salafiyya), part 3, 1933 (Box 22, Folder 6)
  - Ḥaqīl, Ḥamad ibn Ibrāhīm. ʻAbd al-ʻAzīz fī al-tārīkh: tārīkh wa-adab (Beirut: [Muʼassasat al-Maʻārif]), 1968 (Box 23, Folder 1)
  - al-Haṭalānī, Muḥammad ibn Ibrāhīm. Dīwān ash'ār nabaṭīyah min al-jazīrat al-'arabīyah., A.H. 1430 (2010 C.E.) (Box 23, Folder 2)
  - al-Haṭalānī, Muḥammad ibn Ibrāhīm. Dīwān al-dur al-mumtāz min al-shi'r al-nabaṭī al-qadīm., Undated, circa A.H. 1430 (2010 C.E.) (Box 23, Folder 3)
  - Ibn ʻĪsá, Ibrāhīm ibn Ṣāliḥ. 'Iqd al-durar fī mā waqaʿ fī Nājd min al ḥawādith. [String of pearls about what happened in Najd at end of 13th century AH and the 14th century]. (Damascus: Matba'at al-'Amumiyah[?]), 1953 (Box 23, Folder 4)
  - Ibn ʻĪsá, Ibrāhīm ibn Ṣāliḥ. Kitāb ʻIqd al-durar fīmā waqaʻa fi Najd min ḥawādith fī akhir qarn al-thālith ʻashar wa-awwal al-rābiʻ ʻashar [Book of the string of pearls in what concerns events in Nejd in the latter part of the 13th century and the first part of the 14th century], (Riyadh: Maktabah al-ʻArabīyah al-Saʻūdīyah), undated, circa 1960s (Box 23, Folder 5)
  - Ibn Laʻbūn, Ḥamad ibn Muḥammad. Tārīkh Ḥamad ibn Muḥammad Ibn Laʻbūn, al-Wāʼilī al-Ḥanbalī al-Najdī (78 pages, photocopied), 1357 A.H. (circa 1938 C.E.) (Box 23, Folder 6)
  - Khuwayṭir, ʻAbd al-ʻAzīz ibn ʻAbd Allāh. ʻUthmān ibn Bishr: manhajuhu wa-maṣādiruh (al-Riyāḍ: [publisher not identified]), 1970 (Box 23, Folder 7)
  - Lerrick, Alison. Riwāyāt min taghrībat Banī Hilāl: wa-ḥurūb Āl Ḍaygham (Riyadh: Maṭābiʻ al-Farazdaq al-Tijārīyah), 1985 (Box 23, Folder 8)
  - Lewin, Bernhard. Book of Plants of Abu Ḥanīfah ad-Dīnawarī (Uppsala: Lundequistska bokhandeln), 1953 (Box 24, Folder 1)
  - al-Māzinī, Ibrāhīm ʻAbd al-Qādir. Riḥlat al-Ḥijāz [Voyage to Hejaz], [Cairo]: [Maṭbaʻat Fuʼād], [1930] (Box 24, Folder 2)
    General
    OCLC: 44071606
  - Part 2: Bedouins of the Sinai (begins at p. 239) [Arabic, unidentified author]. (Box 24, Folder 3)
  - Rihānī. Amīn al. Tarīkh Najd wa-mulḥaqātih. [Life story of King Abdulaziz, King of Hejaz and Nejd and its dependencies] Beirut, self-printed (Dar al Rihani), 4th edition, 1927, reprinted in 1975 (Box 24, Folder 4)
  - Rubay'an, Fahd al Mohamed al. al-'Uraynāt. Vol. 1 (AH 1398). (relates to Subay'an tribal history) (Box 24, Folder 5)
  - Ṣafrānī, ʻAlī al-Ḥamad.. Diwān anwar al afkar., v. 1 (The Lights of Sa'd] [Nabati poetry] AH 1377 (Box 24, Folder 6)
  - Ṣafrānī, ʻAlī al-Ḥamad. Min al-bādīyah, vol. 3 (Makkah: Maṭābiʻ Dār al-Thaqāfah), AH 1377 (1957 C.E.) (Box 24, Folder 7)
  - Āl Ṣāliḥ al-Dawsarī, Muḥammad ibn Mushʻī. al-Kunūz al-shaʻbīyah, al-rumūz al-ʻArabīyah (Cairo: Dār al-Jīl lil-Ṭibāʻah) (1), 1961 (Box 25, Folder 1)
  - Āl Ṣāliḥ al-Dawsarī, Muḥammad ibn Mushʻī. al-Kunūz al-shaʻbīyah, al-rumūz al-ʻArabīyah (Cairo: Dār al-Jīl lil-Ṭibāʻah) (2), 1961 (Box 25, Folder 2)
  - Āl Ṣāliḥ al-Dawsarī, Muḥammad ibn Mushʻī. al-Kunūz al-shaʻbīyah, al-rumūz al-ʻArabīyah (Cairo: Dār al-Jīl lil-Ṭibāʻah) (3), 1961 (Box 25, Folder 3)
  - Āl Ṣāliḥ al-Dawsarī, Muḥammad ibn Mushʻī. al-Kunūz al-shaʻbīyah, al-rumūz al-ʻArabīyah (Cairo: Dār al-Jīl lil-Ṭibāʻah) (4), 1961 (Box 25, Folder 4)
  - Sāmarrāʾī, ʻĀmir Rashīd al. Mabāḥith fī al-adab al-shaʻbī. [Researches into popular literature] (Baghdad, 1964) (Box 25, Folder 5)
  - Sibāʻī, Aḥmad. Tārīkh Makkah: dirāsāt fī al-siyāsah wa-al-ʻilm wa-al-ijtimāʻ wa-al-ʻumrān, v.1. (Mecca, AH 1380) (Box 25, Folder 6)
  - Sibāʻī, Aḥmad. Tārīkh Makkah: dirāsāt fī al-siyāsah wa-al-ʻilm wa-al-ijtimāʻ wa-al-ʻumrān, v.2. (Mecca, AH 1380) (Box 25, Folder 7)
  - Thumayrī, Mohamed ibn Aḥmad al. Al-funūn al-shaʻbīyah al jazirat al 'Arabīyah [Popular arts in the Arabian Peninsula], 1972 (Box 26, Folder 1)
  - ʻUbayyid, ʻAbd al-Raḥmān ʻAbd al-Karīm, al-. Qabīlat al-ʻawāzim :dirāsah ʻan aṣlihā wa-mujtamaʻihā wa-diyārihā[Al Awazim tribe: Study about its origins, its social structure, and its lands] (Kuwait: Maktabat al-Ādāb), 1971 (Box 26, Folder 2)
  - 'Uqaylān, Aḥmad Farad al. Jināyat al-shiʿr al-ḥurr [The crime of free poetry]. Literary Club of Abhah, 1982 (Box 26, Folder 3)
  - Ūrī, Muḥammad Saʻūd. al-Riḥlah al-Saʻūdīyah al-Ḥijāzīyah al-Najdīyah (Cairo), A.H. 1349 [1930] (Box 26, Folder 4)
  - Wahba, Ḥāfiẓ. Jazīrat al-ʿArab fī al qarn al-ʿishrīn: Peninsula of the Arabs in the 20th century. Cairo, 1946 (Box 26, Folder 5)
  - Ẓāhirī, Abdulrahman ibn 'Aqil al. Āl al-Jabrāʼ fī al-tārīkh wa-al-adab. [re sheikhs of Shammar tribe in Nejd and Syria], 1983 (Box 26, Folder 6)
  - Zāmil, Abdullah al Ali al Mansūr al. Aṣdaq al-bunūd fī ta'rīkh Abdulaziz al Saud [Most truthful records of the history of Abdulaziz al Saud]. (Box 27, Folder 1)
  - al-ʿArab [journal]. [article on Saudi history/literature]. Ed. Hamad, 1978 (Box 27, Folder 2)
  - Abu Athera, Said Salman. Love and mockery: …Bedouin poetry from Jordan and Sinai (abstract, undated, Oxford) (Box 27, Folder 3)
  - Abu Athera, Said Salman. Tribal poetry of the Tarabin and Huwaytat tribes (1) (doctoral dissertation, University of Glasgow, 1995) (Box 27, Folder 4)
  - Abu Athera, Said Salman. Tribal poetry of the Tarabin and Huwaytat tribes (2) (doctoral dissertation, University of Glasgow, 1995) (Box 27, Folder 5)
  - Ageili, al-, Mahmoud S. The settlement of the nomadic tribes in the Northern Province: Saudi Arabia (doctoral dissertation, University of Manchester, 1986) (Box 27, Folder 6)
  - Boot, J.W.A. The tribe in the modern Arabian Peninsula: Abu Dhabi, a case study. (graduation essay, University of Leiden, 1995) (Box 27, Folder 7)
- Photographs and miscellaneous
  Materials currently in process.
  - Slides: 1989 fieldwork in Saudi Arabia
    - Slides: inventory list, by alphanumeric code (Box 28, Folder 1)
    - Slides: Ab 1 - Ab 20 (19 images), September - December 1989 (Box 28, Folder 2)
    - Slides: Ab 21 - Ac 5 (20 images), September - December 1989 (Box 28, Folder 3)
    - Slides: Ac 6 - Ac 25 (20 images), September - December 1989 (Box 28, Folder 4)
    - Slides: Ac 26 - Ad 7 (19 images), September - December 1989 (Box 28, Folder 5)
    - Slides: Ad 9 - Ad 28 (20 images), September - December 1989 (Box 28, Folder 6)
    - Slides: Ad 29 - Ae 15 (20 images), September - December 1989 (Box 28, Folder 7)
    - Slides: Ae 16 - Ae 35, September - December 1989 (Box 28, Folder 8)
    - Slides: Ae 36, Ha 1 - Ha 19, plus four unlabeled (24 images), September - December 1989 (Box 28, Folder 9)
    - Slides: Ha 20 - Hb 3 (20 images), September - December 1989 (Box 28, Folder 10)
    - Slides: Hb 4 - Hb 25 (20 images), September - December 1989 (Box 28, Folder 11)
    - Slides: Hb 26 - Hc 6, plus 2 unlabeled (22 images), September - December 1989 (Box 28, Folder 12)
    - Slides: Hc 4 - Hc 27 (20 images), September - December 1989 (Box 28, Folder 13)
    - Slides: Hc 28, Da 13 - 16; Db 7, 15-16; Dc 5-6a, 29-33 (20 images), September - December 1989 (Box 28, Folder 14)
    - Slides: Db 18 - 27; Dc 7-14; plus one image of Bkheitan (21 images), September - December 1989 (Box 28, Folder 15)
    - Slides: Dc 15 - 39 (20 images), September - December 1989 (Box 28, Folder 16)
    - Slides: Dc 41; Dd 6-14; and unnumbered, of Dindan, September - December 1989 (Box 28, Folder 17)
    - Slides: Dc 35-36, 40; Dd 1-29 (21 images), September - December 1989 (Box 28, Folder 18)
    - Slides: Dc 1-4; Db 29-36; Dd 30-36 (20 slides), September - December 1989 (Box 28, Folder 19)
    - Slides: De 5-24 (20 images), September - December 1989 (Box 28, Folder 20)
    - Slides: De 25-36, plus images numbered 1-8, chiefly of Ibn Betla (20 images), December 1989 (Box 28, Folder 21)
    - Slides: 9 - 21 (9 images), December 1989 (Box 28, Folder 22)
  - Slides: 1994 fieldwork in Saudi Arabia
    - Inventory of slides (numbered) from 1994 trip (Box 29, Folder 1)
    - Slides: A3 - A20, chiefly of Dindan, March - April 1994 (Box 29, Folder 2)
    - Slides: A21 - A40, plus unnumbered slides, and DVD of images (28 images), March - April 1994 (Box 29, Folder 3)
    - Slides: A41 - B15, chiefly of Ibn Betla and Bkheitan (20 images), March - April 1994 (Box 29, Folder 4)
    - Slides: B16 - B35, chiefly of Ibn Betla's camp (20 images), March - April 1994 (Box 29, Folder 5)
    - Slides: B36 - C6, chiefly of Ibn Betla (19 images), March - April 1994 (Box 29, Folder 6)
    - Slides: C7 - C26 (20 images), March - April 1994 (Box 29, Folder 7)
    - Slides: C27 - C40 (14 images), March - April 1994 (Box 29, Folder 8)
    - Slides: D1 - D20 (19 images), March - April 1994 (Box 29, Folder 9)
    - Slides: D22 - E8, including images from Salalah, Oman (19 images), March - April 1994 (Box 29, Folder 10)
    - Slides: E12 - E31, mostly of Oman, and Empty Quarter (20 images), March - April 1994 (Box 29, Folder 11)
    - Slides: E32 - F4, Oman - Dhofar, Empty Quarter, March - April 1994 (Box 29, Folder 12)
  - Slides: general
    - Visit to Nifi, hometown of poet Ibn Sbayyil (38 slides), June 1989 (Box 29, Folder 13)
    - Visit to poet Dubais ("poet of the coffee pot"), plus images of vegetation, near Hail (11 slides), summer 1989 (Box 29, Folder 14)
    - Rafha: Khazraj family, Darb Zubayd, and driver for trip to Nefud (11 slides), summer 1989 (Box 29, Folder 15)
    - Trip between Riyadh and Makkah (7 slides), 1989 (Box 29, Folder 16)
    - Various, Saudi Arabia (7 slides), 1994 (Box 29, Folder 17)
    - With Bkheitan and Saad Sowayyan (10 slides), undated, circa late 1990s (Box 29, Folder 18)
    - Visit to Dindan, and house of Bkheitan (13 slides), undated, circa late 1990s (Box 29, Folder 19)
    - Dindan, courtyard of house of Mitrits (18 slides), undated, circa late 1990s (Box 29, Folder 20)
    - Dindan, Bkheitan, view from Hotel Tharawat in Wadi Dawasir (11 slides), undated, late 1990s (Box 29, Folder 21)
    - Bkheitan, Muḥammed ibn Withaylān of al-Misā'rah, and ostrich feather trophy (18 slides), undated, circa late 1990s (Box 29, Folder 22)
    - Locations in and around Jerusalem, during research for book "Onzalig Jeruzalem" (folder 1, 16 slides), undated, circa 1995-1996 (Box 29, Folder 23)
    - Locations in and around Jerusalem, during research for book "Onzalig Jeruzalem" (folder 2, 19 slides), undated, circa 1995-1996 (Box 29, Folder 24)
    - Saudi Arabia, various, unidentified (18 slides), undated, circa 1989-1994 (Box 29, Folder 25)
  - Prints
    - Various, trips in Saudi Arabia (110 prints), 1987-1989 (Box 30, Folder 1)
    - Visit to Nifi, hometown of poet Ibn Sbayyil (31 prints), summer 1989 (Box 30, Folder 2)
    - Individual poets: Dindan, ibn Betla, Muhamed al-Hanāya, Nābit ibn Dāfir, Nāsir ibn Rubī'ān, and others, spring 1994 (Box 30, Folder 3)
    - Individual poets: Dindan, Ibn Betla, Bkheitan, others (15 prints), 1994-2000 (Box 30, Folder 4)
    - Contact prints and negatives (black and white): images used in Brill publications, 1989 (Box 30, Folder 5)
- Sound recordings [in processing], 1989-2004
- Video recordings [in processing], 1995-2017